Guide to the Howard E. Buswell papers and photographs 1822-1965
Western Washington University, Center for Pacific Northwest Studies
- Audio Collection, 1956-1964; Series XIV
  - Knute Aker and Mrs. Aker, undated (Reel-to-reel Reel #11)
    Cassette Tape #1: Interview with Knute Aker who lives in the Nooksack area between Wiser Lake and Nugents Corner. Mr. Aker took a homestead in 1886 after arriving in U.S. in 1883 from Norway. Mr. Aker discusses how homesteads were cleared of their timber, and floating logs down the Nooksack River to be boomed. The hop business, and Mr. Aker's involvement in it. Mr. Aker speaks of being a Norwegian in the Northwest and seeking other Norwegian's. Mr. Aker speaks of taking the stage from Portland to Seattle. Mr. Aker speaks of taking a canoe to Nooksack Crossing. Mr. Aker speaks of working for Vanburen on his hop field. Mr. Aker describes Vanburen. Mr. Aker speaks of his various experiences working in Whatcom County. He speaks of being taken advantage of by Vanburen, who didn't pay him for his labor. Mr. Aker speaks of finding and acquiring a homestead. Mr. Aker speaks of his benefactor Dr. Johnson, who gave him employment and helped him find a homestead.
    Cassette Tape #2: Mr. Aker tells how Dr. Johnson, in the end, tried to scheme him out of his homestead. (Break in tape where reel was finished) Mr. Aker speaks to proving up his homestead. Mr. Aker speaks to the log jam between Everson and Lynden. Mr. Aker talks about the timber on the riverbanks and the sloughs. Mr. Aker speaks of working on the Cascade Railroad to obtain lumber from pilings for his homestead. Mr. Aker talks about Captain Siegel. Howard asks about the steam boats that ran on the river. Mr. Aker recalls the steam boats when they delivered his cast iron stove. The Advance, The Triumph and The Edith R. were the three main steam boats on the Nooksack as Mrs. Aker's recalls. Mr. Aker recalls the Indians as they traveled on the river by canoe. Mr. Aker recalls the Indian travelers from Canada fondly. Howard reads an article written about Mr. Knute Akers and his trials to obtain an homestead. Mr. Akers talks about clearing his land with stump pullers. Howard speaks of growing up on a strawberry farm in Ferndale. Howard concludes with Mr. Akers and interviews Mrs. Akers, formerly Ms. Door. Her family arrived in 1882. Mrs. Akers speaks of her family's early travels around the country, from Florida to Nebraska and then to Lynden.
    Cassette Tape #3: Mrs. Aker tells how her father ran across literature by Hugh Eldridge on Whatcom County, which enticed him to come to the area. Mrs. Aker tells how her father came to give Wiser Lake its English name.
  - Sam Allen, Carl Bell, Philip Clark and Mary Birdsell Brown, 1956 December 20 (Reel-to-reel Reel #12)
    Cassette Tape #1: December 20, 1956. Interview begins without introductions. Sam, Phil and Carl recall people they knew in the early days - George Swiloose, Delarmer, George Byzer. Speaks to the murder by George Swiloose of the sheriff, Ryan Easterbrook who was pushed over a bank and a settler by the name of Moe. Speaks to the escape and plight of George Swiloose. Howard speaks to seeing George Swiloose on his property in Gooseberry point. Sam and Carl recall coming to Bellingham by steamer boat, arriving at Old Colony Warf. Carl recalls the timber in the area upon his arrival in the late 1800s. Howard asks about Sam George's house, its location in the "old days," and its status as the oldest building in Marietta. Phil disagrees and asserts a different building as the oldest. Everyone speaks to the store in Marietta - previous owners. Howard talks about his father's strawberry business. Howard talks about his father's chicken farming business. Carl talks about his farm in Marietta. Howard recalls Carl driving his cattle. Howard takes a few pictures of the group (then it being quite a process). Mary Brown joins the picture taking fracas.
    Cassette Tape #2: Mary introduces herself. Mary speaks to working at Wannamakers. Mary speaks about seeing Charley. (Break in tape where reel was changed). Discussion concerning store owners in Marietta. Howard asks about the first class that attended the school in Marietta in 1890, he reads a list of names from the census of 1890. Howard reads a school roll list from 1891. Carl speaks about his father working in a cedar mill. Mary speaks about her husband Harvey Brown. Carl speaks at length to his wife's plum pudding. Howard concludes. Howard marvels that these men whom he interviewed could be as old as they are, and at the same time have so little of an education. Sam Allen states that Marietta is not named after his sister Mary Jane. Sam says John Tennant named Marietta after a town in Iowa. John (Nichols) says that Tennant and the Allens were sitting together and Tennant suggested Mary to honor Mrs. Allen's daughter Mary. Tennant then suggested the addition of etta to Mary to arrive at Marietta. Marietta school house located behind Wannamakers' store behind the alley. Howard speaks to his conferral with Jeffcott on the matter of naming Marietta, and Jeffcott confirms that Tennant was never in Iowa, and there is no Marietta, Iowa. Howard reads from Mrs. Roth's book to discern Tennant's travels around the country to see if Tennant named Marietta after Marietta, Texas from which Tennant hails.
    Cassette Tape #3: Interview begins with Sam Allen, Phil Clark and Carl Bell. (Reel begins on second side). All three men attended the first class at the Marietta School in 1891. Carl Bell speaks about transportation into Bellingham. Carl Bell speaks about using the cross-cut saw, and nearly cutting his finger clear off. Sam Allen talks about his cedar shake house. Howard speaks about how the land was obtained for the school at Marietta. All converse on how logs were brought in for the construction of the Marietta school. Sam recalls his brothers attending the Sehome school. Carl Bell reads a love poem that he wrote to his first beau in grade school. Carl Bell recalls manning the belfry at the Marietta school. Carl Bell recalls those he knew living in the Marietta area who had children that went to school with him. Howard reads from MacDonald's account book as to whom the mill operators were. Sam, Carl and Phil recall those mill owners they knew. Howard asks about Morrison, who was contracted to clear the log jam and had a mill also. Carl Bell recalls the pile boom. Sam speaks about the diversion of the river so that the white settlers could fish without the Native fisherman obstructing them. Carl recalls the Edith, a steam boat on the river, tipping and spilling its haul. Sam speaks about the location of Treaty Rock. Carl recalls taking a canoe up Slater Slough carrying Lizzie Slater's body to her funeral.
    Cassette Tape #4: (Tape breaks where reel was changed). Howard asks Sam about his family history, i.e. when his father, Solomon Allen brought his wife back from the Fraser River Valley. Carl and Phil recall the teachers at Marietta school, i.e. Christine McLeod etc. Phil and Carl talk about Albert Mormon, a local banjo player. Carl speaks about Pete Hammer's ice house. Carl and Phil recall Dead Man's Point and Strand's Point and who was buried there. Howard, Phil and Carl recall Emily Mohrmann, Albert Mohrmann's wife. Carl recalls Anna Wallace. Carl, Sam and Phil help Howard identify people in some of his pictures. Carl Bell recalls selling cars to the Native Americans in the area.
    Cassette Tape #5: Howard asks about Sam Allen's father, who was the first settler of Marietta. Sam disputes that Marietta was named after his sister Mary Jane. Sam claims that John Tennant named Marietta after his home town in Iowa, not after his sister Mary. Phil, Carl and Sam continue to identify pictures. End(cont. with tapes 1 and 2).
  - Gaff McGlinn, undated (Reel-to-reel Reel #13)
    Cassette Tape #1: Gaff McGlinn on the PAF (Pacific American Fisheries). McGlinn speaks on who started the PAF. Franko-American canning company was the first name for the PAF in 1900. Speaks about the cannery at the bottom of Harris Avenue in Bellingham. Speaks about E.B. Deming, who was important in the salmon business. In 1901 the PAF put up 350,000 cases of hand-packed, mechanically soddered, canned sock-eye salmon. In 1902 the PAF changed hands and "the great salmon trust" was developed. Onfroy as the founder and organizer of the PAF in 1888-9. McGlinn recounts the transition of the PAF to a man named Receiver and under him the PAF went into the PPNM. In 1907 Deming bought back the PAF for $300,000, which included all the fish traps in the San Juan islands and the canneries. McGlinn attests that the PAF would not buy from the Native fish traps locations. McGlinn discusses Proposition 77, which was to regulate fish traps and purse seines. In 1934 Deming sold his interests in the PAF for $1,000,000. McGlinn speaks about Onfroy. McGlinn speaks about how salmon were obtained from the star scows with a hose, how salmon were pitched, cleaned, butchered and slimed. McGlinn describes the canning process from the steaming and puncturing of the fish to the scraping, drying and cooling. Then to the labeling of the cans, which was done by hand.
    Cassette Tape #2: McGlinn speaks about the Allsop trap in Lummi that took hundreds of thousands of pounds a day. Howard and McGlinn recall Captain Finley who piloted the Calendar around the traps in the Islands. (Tape breaks where reel was changed). McGlinn recalls the Uwanda and the Alpha going down in the Straits. McGlinn speaks about the fish pirates in the Straits. The fish pirates were known to bribe fish trap watchmen and take fish from the fish traps to sell on the open market. The fish pirates were known as legitimate fisherman who were disgruntled with the PAF's monopoly on fish traps. Howard and McGlinn recall various PAF Captains and workers. McGlinn talks about his wages. McGlinn, at length, speaks about working under Mr. Laythem.
    Cassette Tape #3: McGlinn recalls how liquor was stowed on the PAF boats during Prohibition.
  - Bill Cunningham, 1963 Feburary 26 (Reel-to-reel Reel #14)
    Cassette Tape #1: Interview with Bill Cunningham who came to the area in 1900 from Kansas. Bill Cunningham talks about working in the saw mills in Marietta. Howard asks about the shifting of the Nooksack channel in 1906-1908. Bill speaks about how the channel was cut at night with dynamite to divert it away from the Indian village to Marietta to bring in drinking water and to create an unobstructed access to the fish. Howard asks as to whom was involved in cutting the new channel. Cunningham names off a bunch of people. Cunningham claims the reaction from the Indians to the diversion of the river course was mote, because the Lummi fished off the reservation. Howard asks about bridges in the area, i.e. the steel bridge at Clarks, which was moved after the channel of the Nooksack was diverted. Howard talks about the Marietta bridge. Howard asks about Taylor's muskrat farm. Cunningham talks about Taylor's Creek and Taylor's slough. Cunningham and Howard recall the owners of the store in Marietta. Howard reads a list of the Marietta fisherman. Howard asks about fish pirates. Cunningham attests to having a hand in the fish pirating business. Cunningham discusses hauling pilings from Stuart Island. Howard asks about Frank Wright of Lummi Island. Cunningham attests to working for Frank Wright. Cunningham recalls when Frank Wright bought land in Marietta and built a smokehouse. Cunningham recalls the early priests or churches in Marietta. Some on fires in the area. Cunningham speaks about fishing.
    Cassette Tape #2: Cunningham recalls some of the elder Indians he knew. Cunningham recalls MacDonald's store. (Break in tape where reel was changed) Cunningham recalls MacDonald's canoe, and the totem poles at Portage. Cunningham tells the story of John Jacob and Jacob John, who were two Lummis who were swimming in the Bay and saw the Northern Indians coming to raid and warned the village at Portage. Howard recalls when the village at Portage was abandoned. Cunningham recalls going to the smokehouse on Portage to watch the dancers. Howard speaks about Thomas Jefferson's claim as to seeing thousands of canoes at the Portage for a gathering. Howard and Cunningham recall the summer gatherings in Lummi. Cunningham recalls hogs on the tideflats. Howard claims to have a picture of hogs getting clams on the tideflats in Lummi. Howard and Cunningham speak about Sam George's house.
  - Raymond Green and Mrs. Albert Mohrmann, 1956 October 15 (Reel-to-reel Reel #15)
    Cassette Tape #1: Raymond Green, on Oct. 15, 1956. Picnic at Frank Wright's on Village Point in 1914. Raymond Green speaks about why the picnic was given by Frank Wright for the Indians. Picnic as a commemoration of the salmon running (i.e. The First Salmon Ceremony). Green speaks about what he witnessed at the picnic, the first salmon ceremony for example, and dancing. Green speaks about Francis Hillaire. Green recalls the various masks used during the dancing. Green recalls the traditional fishing equipment displayed at the picnic. Green speaks about how reef nets were used by the Indians traditionally. Green speaks about sun drying fish. Green speaks about the technique of filleting fish that was claimed to be responsible for keeping flies and such away. Green speaks about the dance that commemorated the end of the raiding by the Northern Indians. Green speaks about being adopted into the Lummi tribe during the picnic at Frank Wright's. Green attests to being given a piece of parchment with "Hýu' Sion" (Hýyi(Great/Large) Siam(Person of high esteem/respect))" written on it as evidence of his "adoption." Howard speaks about his recollections of the Lummi language being spoken by the Lummi, and the loss of the language. Green recalls his knowledge of the Lummi language, (which is more a mix of Chinook Jargon and a mixing of words from many dialects of the region.) Green continues speaking about the picnic. He discusses Frank Wright's ship. Green attests to the amicable relationship between Wright and Lummi people, in the way that he allowed the Lummi to fish off his land, and he bought their harvest. Green attests to the picnic being John Alexis', Hillaire's, McKluskey's and Wright's idea. The picnic was given exclusively for the Indians. Howard speaks about the pictures he obtained from Mrs. Wright (the third one) portraying the picnic and one showing about ten Indian canoes with the cannery in the background.
    Cassette Tape #2: Howard asks Green about the paucity of pictures of the actual ceremonies. Howard asks about the "Austrian-Lummi squabble." Green discusses the conflict over the fish traps. Green speaks about Commissioner Darwin, who gave permission to non-Natives, here Austrians, to dock their purse seines on reservation land. Then there was a $1,000 fine for fishing illegally on tribal land. Darwin overrode this restriction, and Green gave the Lummi permission to confiscate the Austrians' seines when they docked at the reservation. This went to court and confiscation was deemed just and the Austrian's had to pay the fines. Green talks about the fish trap at Point Francis on the Lummi side. Howard asks about the herring traps at the Portage. Howard and Green talk about the oyster beds at the Portage. Howard concludes.
    Cassette Tape #3: Mrs. Albert Mohrmann reads a little poem that she wrote as a young girl in the first school in Ferndale. Howard explains how a reel to reel tape recorder works to Mrs. Mohrmann. Mrs. Mohrmann talks about the first school house in Ferndale, its location and such. Mrs. Mohrmann recalls going to school with Alice Eldridge. Mrs. Mohrmann reads her poem again. Howard recalls giving speeches in school. Howard and Hilda Mohrmann recall Jeffcott. Mrs. Mohrmann recalls being a janitor for the school. (Tape is blank for about 30 sec. where reel has been repaired.) Mrs. Mohrmann recalls Billy Clark who ran the ferry and had an Indian wife. Howard and Mrs. Mohrmann discuss the mixed families in the area. Mrs. Mohrmann talks about Maria Wynn. Mrs. Mohrmann discusses the Cedargrove post office in Marietta, which her husband ran. Howard asks about the conversion of the Lummi Post Office to the Marietta Post Office. Mrs. Mohrmann speaks about her children and Dr. Van Zandt. Howard asks about the Allens and the Dalys. Hilda Mohrmann speaks about the location of the "Alice Eldridge school." Mrs. Mohrmann recalls Dr. Mayfield as her teacher, and her school days with Lizzie Slater. Mrs. Mohrmann recalls Johnny Slater. Mrs. Mohrmann recalls taking the steamboat to Marietta.
  - John Nichols, undated (Reel-to-reel Reel #16)
    Cassette Tape #1: John Nichols speaks about the first boat he remembers that was built in Marietta, called the Skookum, which was a steamboat that carried lumber and hauled barges. The Skookum was powered with a "brick-yard boiler." John talks about where the mill was and where the shipyards were in Marietta. John speaks about how steamboat boilers were made and operated. Specifically, how the boilers were encased in bricks to keep in the heat. John speaks about the Auntie Em Pence, the main, functioning steamboat. Howard asks about bridges, specifically the many bridges over the Nooksack in Marietta. John speaks about taking out the piling of the first bridge over the Nooksack at Clarks. Howard and John continue talking about bridges. John tells a story about dickering over lumber with George Swiloose. Howard asks about the Henry Roger's mill in Marietta. John speaks about the first rural telephone in Marietta. Howard asks about David Daly. Howard and John recall who sported a full beard in the older days. Howard asks about Fred Lane-Taylor. John recalls the story of Fred Taylor pursuing white suitors for his daughters who had a Native American mother. Howard recalls Irene Bond (Lane), one of Fred Taylor's daughter's. John speaks about the law of 1871 that required all "sqwa-men"(white men who lived with Indian women) to marry their Native American partners. Howard recalls Johnny Hyatt. John recalls George Smith and other township assessors.
    Cassette Tape #2: John speaks about serving as a township assessor. John speaks about assessing logs at the mill, and the onnery timber workers. (Break in Tape where reel was changed). John continues speaking about his assessing work. John speaks about working as a meat cutter (at great length) and delivering his cuts around the county up to Custer. John continues to speak about his butchering business for the remainder of the tape.
    Cassette Tape #3: Howard leaves the room and there is a period of silence. John speaks about George Dillenger. Howard concludes with John Nichols. End. Tape contains about 5 minutes of interview time.
  - Ingwold Iverson, 1959 September 28 (Reel-to-reel Reel #17)
    Cassette Tape #1: Howard introduces Mr. Ingwold Iverson who will show slides and present a discussion on Alaska. Howard notes that the slides used in this presentation will be donated to him. [These tapes really only have value in coordination with the slides] Iverson speaks about the Carslile Cannery to begin. Iverson speaks about the salmon fishing in Alaska halibut and churches. Iverson speaks about Father Duncan. Iverson speaks about the PAF cannery in Alaska. Iverson speaks briefly to many various unrelated topics as they pertain to his slide show: evidences of gold mines, Alaskan sled dogs, Dawson's city, Russian Orthodox churches, bears, Aleutian islands, Sitka Alaska and the fur trade, salmon spawning, various ships.
    Cassette Tape #2: Various ships continues, seal and sea otter hunting, PAF ships, harpoon guns, whales killed by harpoon, various other stories about his excursion into Alaska, sled-dog teams, Sitka in the early days, Mt. McKinley, Various famous rivers and glaciers.
    Cassette Tape #3: Tides, more steam ships, (tape breaks where reel was changed), S.S. Dora and a suspended horse, Copper River bridge, Chuckanut Pass, PAF canneries and traps, Rawle Anderson's plane and subsequent crash, Iverson gives a conclusion of his experiences and knowledge of Alaska.
    Cassette Tape #4: Iverson continues his conclusion, or ode to Alaska. Howard asks Iverson to run through the maps on his slides. (Tape breaks where reel was changed). Iverson talks about the Russian exploration expeditions to Alaska. Iverson talks about the purchase of the Alaska territory by the U.S.A.
  - Albert Mohrmann, undated (Reel-to-reel Reel #18)
    Cassette Tape #1: Howard Buswell introduces the content of the tape as "Albert's March," which is a waltz that as performed, composed and recorded by Mr. Albert Morhmann. Howard talks about the weather. Howard gives the date of his parents marriage. [The music begins abruptly]. Howard gives more background to Albert Mohrmann. Second side of the reel begins with a second playing of the waltz. Then, for good measure, the waltz played again.
  - Services at Marietta Indian Mission, 1958 April 20; 1958 May 4 (Reel-to-reel Reel #19)
    Cassette Tape #1: The "Indian-Christian hour" radio broadcast with services by Rev. Harnden. Sister Gerry blesses their Indian neighbors, the Lummi, Nooksack, Swinomish, etc. Mrs. Harnden and others sing a hymn. Sister Gerry spends a good deal of time soliciting donations for the Harnden's boys and girls camp for Indian children. More hymns. Rev. Harnden gives his testimony. Hymn. Rev. Harnden's service. Closing hymn.
    Cassette Tape #2: Hymn. Boys and girls from Lummi Indian Reservation are at the broadcast. Bernice Plaster leads a prayer. Hymn. Sister Gerry reads a poem, "God wants little girls and boys." The Lummi children sing a hymn, "Jesus loves the little children." Jerry Lewis, a Lummi Indian boy, reads a verse from the scriptures; other verses from the scriptures are read by the children. Charles [Freddy] (Toby?) sings a song and reads a verse. Bernice Plaster reads from the scriptures. Norbie, and his sister Regina read scripture. Hymn. Rev. Harnden leads services.
- Map Collection, undated; Series XV
  - Asia, Mexico, California, Northwest U.S. and Canada, 1855-1947 (Map-folder 1)
    To view item level description of maps in the Howard Buswell collection, follow this hyperlink to the map catalog on the Center for Pacific Northwest Studies' website.
  - British Columbia and Northwest Washington, 1859-1947 (Map-folder 2)
  - Northern Pacific Railway; Boundary Survey, 1840; 1846 (Map-folder 3)
  - Washington, Railroads, Counties, Whatcom County, 1857-1955 (Map-folder 4)
  - Dixon Entrance, Puget Sound, 1890-1955 (Map-folder 5)
  - U.S. Coast Survey, Reconnaissance of West Coast, 1853-1866 (Map-folder 6)
  - San Juan Islands, Bellingham Bay, 1841-1955 (Map-folder 7)
  - Bellingham Bay, U.S. Military Road, 1855-1891 (Map-folder 8)
  - Point Roberts; Semiahmoo Bay, 1857-1959 (Map-folder 9)
  - San Juan Island Survey Plat Maps, 1875-1889 (Map-folder 10)
  - Island and Whatcom County Plat Maps, 1863-1889 (Map-folder 11)
  - Island and Whatcom County Plat Maps, 1860-1927 (Map-folder 12)
  - Whatcom County Plat Maps, 1860-1902 (Map-folder 13)
  - Whatcom County - Incorporated Areas - Acme, Bellingham, 1871-1907 (Map-folder 14)
  - Whatcom County - Incorporated Areas - Acme, Bellingham, 1903-1936 (Map-folder 15)
  - Whatcom County - Incorporated Areas - Birch Bay, Blaine, 1884-1911 (Map-folder 16)
  - Whatcom County - Incorporated Areas - Blaine, 1889-1911 (Map-folder 17)
  - Whatcom County - Incorporated Areas - Blue Canyon City, Chuckanut Bay, Clearbrook, Custer, Deming, Drayton, 1889-1902 (Map-folder 18)
  - Whatcom County - Incorporated Areas - Everson, East Lynne, Ferndale, Fairhaven, 1883-1911 (Map-folder 19)
  - Whatcom County - Incorporated Areas - Fairhaven, 1883-1902 (Map-folder 20)